<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

  <preface id="intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      This document tells you how to create applications that look right,
      behave properly, and fit into the MATE user interface as a whole. It
      is written for interface designers, graphic artists and software
      developers who will be creating software for the MATE environment.
      Both specific advice on making effective use of interface elements,
      and the philosophy and general design principles behind the MATE
      interface are covered.
    </para>
    <para>
      These guidelines are meant to help you design and write applications 
      that are
      easy to use and consistent with the MATE desktop. Following these
      guidelines will have many benefits:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Users will learn to use your
	program faster, because interface elements will look and
	behave the way they are used to.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Novice and advanced users alike will be able
	accomplish tasks quickly and easily, because the interface
	won't be confusing or make things difficult.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Your application will have an attractive look
	that fits in with the rest of the desktop.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Your application will continue to look
	good when users change desktop themes, fonts and
	colors.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Your application will be accessible to all
	users, including those with disabilities or special
	needs.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      To help you achieve these goals, these guidelines will cover basic
      interface elements, how to use them and put them together effectively,
      and how to make your application integrate well with the desktop.
    </para>
    <para>
      The recommendations here build on design aspects that have
      worked well in other systems, including Mac OS, Windows, Java
      and KDE. At the same time they retain a uniquely MATE flavor.
    </para>

    <tip><title>Remember...</title>
       <para>Following the guidelines will make your job easier, 
        not harder!</para>
    </tip>

  </preface>

