<chapter id="accessintro-1">

<title>Introduction to Accessibility</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>Section 508</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>
This chapter introduces you to accessibility in the MATE Desktop.
</para>
<para>
All software products should incorporate accessibility features to enable people with disabilities to use the software easily and efficiently. Recent legislation such as Section 508 of the U.S. Rehabilitation Act
heightens awareness of the need to provide accessible software.
</para>
<para>
The MATE Desktop is easy to use and incorporates many accessibility features. Every supported application and utility in the MATE Desktop is designed with accessibility and usability in mind. Users with physical disabilities such as low vision or impaired motor skills can use all of the functionality of the MATE Desktop thanks to the customization tools that are available. These customization tools enable you to fine-tune the appearance and behavior of the desktop.
</para>
<para>
The ability to easily customize the MATE Desktop contributes greatly to the accessibility of the desktop. This guide describes the various options available to
meet your particular needs.
</para>

<section id="quickref">
<title>Quick Reference</title>
<para>
To jump to a specific topic, follow these quick reference links:
</para>
<para>
To hear screen elements spoken to you, see the <link linkend="enable-orca">Orca</link> section.
</para>
<para>
If you need large print, read about <link linkend="themes-4">Choosing Themes</link> and <link linkend="themes-10">Customizing Fonts</link>.
</para>
<para>
To have some or all of the screen magnified, see the <link linkend="ats-2">Magnifier</link> section.
</para>
<para>
If you prefer a pointing device over the keyboard, you can configure an on-screen keyboard for point-and-click typing; see the <link linkend="gok">MATE Onscreen Keyboard (gok)</link> section.
</para>
<para>
If you can only press one key at a time, see the Sticky Keys portion of the <link linkend="dtconfig-14">Configuring an Accessible Keyboard</link> section.
</para>
<para>
If you tend to press keys for too long a time (normally causing inadvertant extra keys), see the Slow Keys portion of the <link linkend="dtconfig-14">Configuring an Accessible Keyboard</link> section.
</para>
<para>
If you tend to press keys multiple times (normally causing inadvertant extra keys), see the Bounce Keys portion of the <link linkend="dtconfig-14">Configuring an Accessible Keyboard</link> section.
</para>
<para>
For further mouse- or pointer-based accessibility support, see the <link linkend="mousetweaks">MouseTweaks</link> and <link linkend="dtconfig-14">Configuring an Accessible Keyboard</link> sections. These tools supply several accessibility aids for pointer devices and keyboards.
</para>
</section>

</chapter>
