<preface id="preface-0">
<title>Preface</title>
<para>
The <citetitle>MATE &manrevision; Desktop 
Accessibility Guide</citetitle> describes how to configure, customize and use the accessibility features of the MATE &manrevision; Desktop.
</para>

<sect1 id="preface-1">
<title>Who Should Read This Guide</title>
<para>
This guide is for users, system administrators, and anyone else who is interested in how the MATE &mateversion; Desktop supports people with disabilities. This guide also addresses the requirements of Section 508 of the U.S. Rehabilitation Act.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="preface-2">
<title>How This Guide Is Organized</title>
<para>This guide is structured in the following manner:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<xref linkend="accessintro-1"/> introduces you to accessibility in the MATE Desktop.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<xref linkend="dtconfig-0"/> describes how to configure the mouse and keyboard to make these devices accessible to more users.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><xref linkend="keynav-0"/> describes how to navigate the MATE Desktop from the keyboard.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<xref linkend="themes-0"/> describes the features and methods you can use to change the appearance of the MATE Desktop. These features can enhance the accessibility of the desktop for users with visual impairments.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<xref linkend="ats-0"/> introduces you to the 
assistive technologies that are available from the MATE Desktop.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<xref linkend="sysadmin-0"/> describes the system administrator tasks that you need to perform before you can use the assistive technologies for the MATE Desktop.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="preface-3">
<title>Related Documentation</title>
<para>
The following manuals are related to this guide:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<citetitle>MATE &manrevision; Desktop System 
Administration Guide</citetitle>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<citetitle>MATE &manrevision; Desktop User Guide
</citetitle>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>
</preface>
