<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
    "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY legal SYSTEM "legal.xml">
<!ENTITY appversion "2.1.6">
<!ENTITY manversion "2.1.0">
<!ENTITY date "May 2002">
<!ENTITY app "Bug Buddy">
]>
<article>
  <nonfinaltag>Translators, enter your name</nonfinaltag>
  <sect1 id="intro">
	<title>Introduction</title>

	<para>
	  <application>&app;</application> is a tool which
	  will guide you through making a bug report as painlessly as possible.
	  You can alter things at any stage, and then either send, save, or
	  abandon the resulting report. This document describes
	  version &appversion; of <application>&app;</application>: note that
	  it has changed substantially in appearance from earlier versions.
	</para>

	<note>
	  <title>Big Bug Buddy Changes</title>
	  <para>
		<application>Bug Buddy</application> has undergone major changes
		recently.
	  </para>
	  <para>
		The Mate bug tracking system is moving from the email-based
		debbugs installation which it originally used to the web-based
		<ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/" type="http">bugzilla
		  installation</ulink>. This is to help deal with bugs more efficiently.
		This means <application>Bug Buddy</application> has been substantially
		rewritten to deal with the bugzilla system. It looks very similar in
		appearance and structure, but be aware that it now talks to bugzillas.
		Reports will only go to the old debbugs system for MATE if bugzilla
		doesn't have a category for the bug.
	  </para>
	  <para>
		This also means that <application>Bug Buddy</application> has currently
		lost the ability to send bugs to the KDE and Debian bug trackers
		directly. Note that you can still save reports for those into a file
		and then mail the file to those trackers yourself.
	  </para>
	</note>

	<para>
	  <application>&app;</application> can be started in a variety
	  of ways:
	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
		<para>
		  Open the <guimenu>main MATE menu</guimenu> and select
		  <menuchoice>
			<guimenu>Applications</guimenu>
			<guisubmenu>Programming</guisubmenu>
			<guimenuitem>Bug Report Tool</guimenuitem>
		  </menuchoice>
		  .
		</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
		<para>
		  Run <command>bug-buddy</command> at the prompt in a terminal such
		  as <application>mate-terminal</application> or
		  <application>xterm</application>.
		</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
		<para>
		  If you are using <application>Caja</application> you can
		  double-click your mouse on a core file to start it.
		</para>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
		<para>
		  When a MATE program experiences a bad crash, a <guilabel>crash
			dialog box</guilabel> is displayed. If
		  <application>&app;</application>
		  is present on the system, then one of the options in the dialog
		  box will be to make a bug-report. Selecting that will lead you
		  to a further dialog box giving you details of the program which
		  crashed. Continuing at this stage will invoke <application>Bug Buddy
		  </application>.
		</para>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
       </para>
	<para>
	  <application>&app;</application> is a very structured program.
	  At any stage you can continue forward or head backwards to correct
	  earlier details, or you can click the <guibutton>Help button</guibutton>
	  to bring up this document.
	</para>
  </sect1>

</article>
