<chapter id="infodesign"> 
  <title>Basic Building Blocks of Information Design</title> 
  <para> This chapter provides a brief introduction to the basic building
	 blocks of information design. You can find information about how to use DocBook
	 tags to create the basic building blocks in the 
	 <ulink
	  url="http://developer.mate.org/projects/gdp/handbook/gdp-handbook/"> 
		<citetitle>MATE Handbook of Writing Software
		  Documentation</citetitle></ulink>. <xref linkend="infoblocks"/> contains
	 examples of some of the information design building blocks in this chapter.
	 </para> 
  <sect1 id="infodesign-2"> 
	 <title>Section Headings</title> 
	 <para> A section heading summarizes the information in the associated
		information block. Use section headings to divide a large body of information
		into logical chunks. </para> 
	 <sect2 id="infodesign-3"> 
		<title>Guidelines for Writing Section Headings</title> 
		<para> Use the following guidelines to write section headings: </para> 
		<itemizedlist> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Use a level-one heading to start a broad subject area.
				Level-one headings are typically generic titles, such as <emphasis>Basic
				Skills</emphasis>, <emphasis>Getting Started</emphasis>, and so on. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Use level-two, level-three, and level-four headings to chunk
				information into easy-to-identify sections. Use specific titles that summarize
				the information in the associated sections. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Do not use more than four heading levels. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Limit the use of level-four headings. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Try to have at least two headings within a section. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Keep headings short. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Use parallel construction in headings of the same level. For
				example, if you use a gerund to start one heading, use a gerund to start all
				headings of the same level in the section. </para> 
			 <informaltable frame="none"> 
				<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0"><colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"
				  colwidth="1.00*"/><colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2.17*"/> 
				  <tbody> 
					 <row> 
						<entry colname="col1" valign="top" align="left" rowsep="0"> 
						  <para> Correct: </para> </entry> 
						<entry colname="col2" valign="top" align="left" rowsep="0"> 
						  <para> To Open a File </para> 
						  <para> To Save a File </para> 
						  <para> To Edit a File </para> </entry> 
					 </row> 
					 <row> 
						<entry colname="col1" valign="top" align="left"> 
						  <para> Incorrect: </para> </entry> 
						<entry colname="col2" valign="top" align="left"> 
						  <para> Opening a File </para> 
						  <para> To Save a File </para> 
						  <para> Edit a File </para> </entry> 
					 </row> 
				  </tbody> 
				</tgroup> 
			 </informaltable> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Avoid starting a heading with an article. </para> 
			 <informaltable frame="none"> 
				<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0"><colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"
				  colwidth="1.00*"/><colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2.17*"/> 
				  <tbody> 
					 <row> 
						<entry colname="col1" valign="top" align="left" rowsep="0"> 
						  <para> Correct: </para> </entry> 
						<entry colname="col2" valign="top" align="left" rowsep="0"> 
						  <para> Caja File Manager </para> </entry> 
					 </row> 
					 <row> 
						<entry colname="col1" valign="top" align="left"> 
						  <para> Incorrect: </para> </entry> 
						<entry colname="col2" valign="top" align="left"> 
						  <para> The Caja File Manager </para> </entry> 
					 </row> 
				  </tbody> 
				</tgroup> 
			 </informaltable> 
		  </listitem> 
		</itemizedlist> 
	 </sect2> 
  </sect1> 
  <sect1 id="infodesign-4"> 
	 <title>Jump Lists</title> 
	 <para> A jump list is a bulleted list of cross-references to the
		subsections in a chapter or section. Jump lists provide a navigational aid for
		the reader. For online documents, use hyperlinks for the cross-references.
		</para> 
	 <sect2 id="infodesign-5"> 
		<title>Guidelines for Writing Jump Lists</title> 
		<para> Use the following guidelines to write jump lists: </para> 
		<itemizedlist> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Use jump lists consistently in your document. If you use a
				jump list at the start of one chapter or section, use a jump list at the start
				of every equivalent section. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Use the exact title of the section you are referencing as the
				text of the jump list item. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Keep all of the items in a jump list on the same page if
				possible. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Do not mix heading levels in the jump list. For example, if a
				chapter contains level-one, level-two, and level-three headings, only list the
				level-one headings in the jump list at the start of the chapter. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		</itemizedlist> 
	 </sect2> 
  </sect1> 
  <sect1 id="infodesign-6"> 
	 <title>Tables</title> 
	 <para> Use tables to present large amounts of detailed information that you
		can structure uniformly. If a paragraph becomes cumbersome and repetitive,
		consider using a table instead. You can use the following types of table:
		</para> 
	 <variablelist> 
		<varlistentry> 
		  <term>Formal table</term> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> A formal table is numbered and has a caption. A formal table
				usually appears in the table of contents of a manual. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		</varlistentry> 
		<varlistentry> 
		  <term>Informal table</term> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> An informal table is not numbered, and does not have a
				caption. An informal table does not usually appear in the table of contents of
				a manual. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		</varlistentry> 
	 </variablelist> 
	 <sect2 id="infodesign-7"> 
		<title>Guidelines for Using Tables</title> 
		<para> Use the following guidelines to create and write the content of
		  tables: </para> 
		<itemizedlist> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Use a complete sentence to introduce the table. Ensure that
				the introductory sentence puts the table information into context. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Do not insert a table between the beginning and end of the
				same sentence. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Write column headings that summarize the information in the
				column. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Use title capitalization rules for column headings and avoid
				end punctuation except where a question mark or ellipsis is required by the
				text. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Avoid starting a column heading with an article. For example,
				use "Rule Name" instead of "The Rule Name". </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Use parallel verb tenses, grammatical construction, voice, and
				punctuation to write the text content of each table column. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Keep column text brief. Remove superfluous words such as
				articles and repetitive phrases in the column heading. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		</itemizedlist> 
		<sect3> 
		  <title>Guidelines for Formal Tables</title> 
		  <itemizedlist> 
			 <listitem> 
				<para> Use a formal table when you want to refer to the table from
				  other sections of the document. </para> 
			 </listitem> 
			 <listitem> 
				<para> Use a formal table when you want the table to appear in the
				  table of contents. </para> 
			 </listitem> 
			 <listitem> 
				<para> Assign an appropriate table caption to a formal table that
				  matches the style of other captions and section headings. Use title
				  capitalization rules for table captions. Position the caption above the
				  graphic. </para> 
			 </listitem> 
		  </itemizedlist> 
		</sect3> 
		<sect3> 
		  <title>Guidelines for Informal Tables</title> 
		  <itemizedlist> 
			 <listitem> 
				<para> Use an informal table when you do not want to refer to the
				  table from other sections of the document. </para> 
			 </listitem> 
			 <listitem> 
				<para> Use an informal table when you do not want the table to
				  appear in the table of contents. </para> 
			 </listitem> 
			 <listitem> 
				<para> Use an informal table to structure information that occurs
				  in text blocks, such as lists of values. </para> 
			 </listitem> 
		  </itemizedlist> 
		</sect3> 
	 </sect2> 
  </sect1> 
  <sect1 id="infodesign-8"> 
	 <title>Graphics</title> 
	 <para> Use graphics to clarify your subject matter. A graphic can be a
		screenshot, diagram, graph, chart, or any graphic element. You can use the
		following types of graphic: </para> 
	 <variablelist> 
		<varlistentry> 
		  <term>Formal graphic</term> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> A formal graphic is numbered and has a caption. A formal
				graphic usually appears in the table of contents of a manual. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		</varlistentry> 
		<varlistentry> 
		  <term>Informal graphic</term> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> An informal graphic is not numbered, and does not have a
				caption. An informal graphic does not appear in the table of contents of a
				manual. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		</varlistentry> 
	 </variablelist> 
	 <sect2 id="infodesign-9"> 
		<title>Guidelines for Using Graphics</title> 
		<para> Use the following guidelines to include graphics in your material:
		  </para> 
		<itemizedlist> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Use graphics to provide additional technical information that
				is not provided by the text. Do not repeat existing text information in graphic
				format. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Where necessary, use a complete sentence to introduce a
				graphic. Use the introductory sentence to put the graphic into context. </para>
			 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Consider the type of material you are writing, and how users access the material, before you include screenshots of the application.
				There are different considerations for online Help and printed manuals. See the
				following sections: 
				<itemizedlist> 
				  <listitem> 
					 <para> <xref linkend="infodesign-10"/></para> 
				  </listitem> 
				  <listitem> 
					 <para> <xref linkend="infodesign-11"/></para> 
				  </listitem> 
				</itemizedlist> </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		</itemizedlist> 
		<sect3> 
		  <title>Guidelines for Formal Graphics</title> 
		  <itemizedlist> 
			 <listitem> 
				<para> Use a formal graphic when you want to refer to the graphic
				  from other sections of the document. </para> 
			 </listitem> 
			 <listitem> 
				<para> Use a formal graphic when you want the graphic to appear in
				  the table of contents. </para> 
			 </listitem> 
			 <listitem> 
				<para> Use a formal graphic for a screenshot at the start of an
				  applet online Help manual. You do not need an introductory sentence for a
				  screenshot of an applet at the start of an applet manual. </para> 
			 </listitem> 
			 <listitem> 
				<para> Assign an appropriate caption to a formal graphic that
				  matches the style of other captions and section headings. Use title
				  capitalization rules for graphic captions. Position the caption above the
				  graphic. </para> 
			 </listitem> 
		  </itemizedlist> 
		</sect3> 
		<sect3> 
		  <title>Guidelines for Informal Graphics</title> 
		  <itemizedlist> 
			 <listitem> 
				<para> Use an informal graphic when you do not want to refer to the
				  graphic from other sections of the document. </para> 
			 </listitem> 
			 <listitem> 
				<para> Use an informal graphic when you do not want the graphic to
				  appear in the table of contents. </para> 
			 </listitem> 
			 <listitem> 
				<para> Use an informal graphic for graphics that occur in text
				  blocks, such as screenshots of buttons or icons. </para> 
			 </listitem> 
		  </itemizedlist> 
		</sect3> 
	 </sect2> 
	 <sect2 id="infodesign-10"> 
		<title>Guidelines for Using Screenshots in Online Help</title> 
		<para> Use the following guidelines for including screenshots in online
		  Help: </para> 
		<itemizedlist> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Include a screenshot of the applet or application at the start
				of the manual for the applet or application. The screenshot enables users to
				verify that the manual describes the same applet or application that they are
				viewing online. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Do not use screenshots indiscriminately in online Help.
				</para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Make sure that each additional screenshot is really necessary.
				Bear in mind that the user usually has the application open in the MATE
				Desktop, so that a screenshot in the Help does not provide any additional
				information. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		</itemizedlist> 
		<para> Before you decide to use screenshots in online Help, consider the
		  following points: </para> 
		<itemizedlist> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Users must scroll screenshots to get to the next piece of
				information. Screenshots slow down the user access to information. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Help that describes everything in text is more accessible to
				users with disabilities than Help with text plus pictures. If a screenshot does
				not provide additional technical information, then the Help is more complex
				than necessary for disabled users. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Usability studies show that users can confuse Help screenshots
				with the real application. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Task-oriented Help requires fewer screenshots than a
				descriptive approach. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> There is a requirement to update screenshots with product
				development. If the screenshot and the product are out-of-step, you risk
				confusing the user. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> There is a requirement for accessibility text for every
				screenshot. You must update this text each time the screenshot is updated.
				There is a risk of the accessibility text being out-of-step with the
				screenshot, or with the application. These factors add to the maintenance load
				for the writer, and can confuse the disabled user. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Screenshots add to the localization burden and cost. The
				localization team has to capture all screenshots in each language. Also,
				translators have to translate the accessibility text associated with each
				screenshot into each language. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		</itemizedlist> 
	 </sect2> 
	 <sect2 id="infodesign-11"> 
		<title>Guidelines for Using Screenshots in Printed Manuals</title> 
		<para> Some MATE Desktop distributions have a requirement to print manuals
		  covering broad topics, such as the 
		  <ulink url="http://www.mate.org/learn/users-guide/2.0/"> 
			 <citetitle>MATE 2.0 Desktop User Guide</citetitle></ulink>. The same
		  manuals are usually also a source of online Help, therefore you need to
		  consider the requirements for both online Help and for printed manuals. Many of
		  the issues associated with screenshots in online Help also apply to screenshots
		  in printed manuals. However, printed manuals are not always used in conjunction
		  with the application running on the MATE Desktop. Therefore, you might need to
		  use more screenshots in printed manuals than in online Help. </para> 
		<para> Use the following guidelines for including screenshots in printed
		  manuals: </para> 
		<itemizedlist> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Do not use screenshots in printed manuals for aesthetic
				purposes. For example, do not use screenshots for the sole purpose of breaking
				up long passages. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Always ensure that there is a user requirement to see a
				screenshot in a specific location. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Always ensure that the screenshots support the text, rather
				than repeat what the text says. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		</itemizedlist> 
	 </sect2> 
  </sect1> 
  <sect1 id="infodesign-12"> 
	 <title>Lists</title> 
	 <para> Lists break information from the standard paragraph format into a
		concise, organized, easy-to-read format. You can use the following types of
		lists: </para> 
	 <itemizedlist> 
		<listitem> 
		  <para> Unnumbered lists, also known as <emphasis>bullet</emphasis>
			 lists or <emphasis>itemized</emphasis> lists </para> 
		</listitem> 
		<listitem> 
		  <para> Numbered lists </para> 
		</listitem> 
		<listitem> 
		  <para> Lists of terms with a description for each term, known as
			 <emphasis>variable</emphasis> lists </para> 
		</listitem> 
	 </itemizedlist> 
	 <sect2 id="infodesign-13"> 
		<title>General Guidelines for Writing Lists</title> 
		<para> Use the following guidelines to write lists: </para> 
		<itemizedlist> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Use unnumbered lists where the entries in the list are of the
				same importance and do not follow a sequence. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Use numbered lists where the entries in the list must follow a
				sequence. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Use variable lists when you need to include short descriptions
				for a list of topics. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Use a complete sentence that ends with a colon to introduce a
				list. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Use a list to put information into context. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Do not continue an introductory sentence after the list.
				</para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Do not connect list items with conjunctions such as "and" or
				"or". </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Begin each list item with the same part of speech. For
				example, in a numbered list begin each list item with a verb. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Capitalize the first word of each list item. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Use a period at the end of each list item, if one of the items
				is a complete sentence. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Do not use a period at the end of each list item, if the items
				are phrases, words, or sentence fragments. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		</itemizedlist> 
	 </sect2> 
	 <sect2 id="infodesign-14"> 
		<title>Writing Unnumbered Lists</title> 
		<para> Use unnumbered lists where the sequence of the information is not
		  important. In addition to the general guidelines listed above, use the
		  following guidelines for writing unnumbered lists: </para> 
		<itemizedlist> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Ensure that all list entries are similar in value. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Where appropriate use a sublist or nested list to further
				break out a complex list entry. For example: </para> 
			 <itemizedlist> 
				<listitem> 
				  <para> Main list entry </para> 
				  <itemizedlist> 
					 <listitem> 
						<para> Sublist entry </para> 
					 </listitem> 
					 <listitem> 
						<para> Sublist entry </para> 
					 </listitem> 
				  </itemizedlist> 
				</listitem> 
				<listitem> 
				  <para> Main list entry </para> 
				</listitem> 
			 </itemizedlist> 
		  </listitem> 
		</itemizedlist> 
	 </sect2> 
	 <sect2 id="infodesign-15"> 
		<title>Writing Numbered Lists</title> 
		<para> Use numbered lists where the sequence of the information is
		  important. For example, use numbered lists for procedures. In addition to the
		  general guidelines listed above, use the following guidelines for writing
		  numbered lists: </para> 
		<itemizedlist> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Only use numbered lists where there are more than two items in
				the list. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> For procedures, use the following guidelines: </para> 
			 <itemizedlist> 
				<listitem> 
				  <para> Use a complete sentence with a period for each step.
					 </para> 
				</listitem> 
				<listitem> 
				  <para> Use a separate step for each action. However, if actions
					 include routine substeps, you can include the substep in the main action. For
					 example, if a step requires the user to press 
					 <keycap>Return</keycap> at the end of the step, you can include
					 "then press 
					 <keycap>Return</keycap>" at the end of the step. </para> 
				</listitem> 
				<listitem> 
				  <para> Where possible begin each step with an active verb in the
					 imperative form. For example: </para> 
				  <orderedlist> 
					 <listitem> 
						<para> Choose 
						  <menuchoice> 
							 <guimenu>File</guimenu> 
							 <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem> 
						  </menuchoice>.</para> 
					 </listitem> 
					 <listitem> 
						<para> Select the file you want to open, then click 
						  <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. </para> 
					 </listitem> 
				  </orderedlist> 
				</listitem> 
			 </itemizedlist> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Use clear and concise text in each step. Avoid redundant
				words. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		</itemizedlist> 
	 </sect2> 
	 <sect2 id="infodesign-21"> 
		<title>Writing Variable Lists</title> 
		<para> You can use a variable list to separate terms from descriptions of
		  the terms, in a list of terms. For example: </para> 
		<para> The dialog contains the following elements: </para> 
		<variablelist> 
		  <varlistentry> 
			 <term> 
				<guilabel>Use Proxy</guilabel> check box</term> 
			 <listitem> 
				<para> Select this option to ... </para> 
			 </listitem> 
		  </varlistentry> 
		  <varlistentry> 
			 <term> 
				<guilabel>Username</guilabel> text box</term> 
			 <listitem> 
				<para> Use this text box to ... </para> 
			 </listitem> 
		  </varlistentry> 
		  <varlistentry> 
			 <term> 
				<guilabel>Password</guilabel> text box</term> 
			 <listitem> 
				<para> Use this text box to ... </para> 
			 </listitem> 
		  </varlistentry> 
		</variablelist> 
	 </sect2> 
  </sect1> 
  <sect1 id="infodesign-16"> 
	 <title>Cross-References</title> 
	 <para> Use cross-references to identify information that is related to a
		specific topic. </para> 
	 <sect2 id="infodesign-17"> 
		<title>Guidelines for Writing Cross-References</title> 
		<para> Use the following guidelines for creating and using
		  cross-references: </para> 
		<itemizedlist> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Use cross-references where related information is already
				described elsewhere in the document and is not essential to the current
				discussion. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Do not include a cross-reference to information that is
				essential for the reader to understand the current discussion. In this
				situation, you should restructure the document to include the information in
				the current discussion, or at least summarize the essential information in the
				current discussion. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Use specific and clear phrases to introduce cross-references.
				</para> 
			 <informaltable frame="none"> 
				<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0"><colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"
				  colwidth="1.00*"/><colspec colnum="2" colname="col2" colwidth="2.17*"/> 
				  <tbody> 
					 <row> 
						<entry colname="col1" valign="top" align="left" rowsep="0"> 
						  <para> Ambiguous: </para> </entry> 
						<entry colname="col2" valign="top" align="left" rowsep="0"> 
						  <para> To configure, see Settings. </para> </entry> 
					 </row> 
					 <row> 
						<entry colname="col1" valign="top" align="left" rowsep="0"> 
						  <para> Clear: </para> </entry> 
						<entry colname="col2" valign="top" align="left" rowsep="0"> 
						  <para> For information about how to configure the applet,
							 see <emphasis>Settings</emphasis>. </para> </entry> 
					 </row> 
				  </tbody> 
				</tgroup> 
			 </informaltable> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Use hyperlinks for cross-references in online documentation.
				</para> 
		  </listitem> 
		</itemizedlist> 
	 </sect2> 
  </sect1> 
  <sect1 id="infodesign-18"> 
	 <title>Tips, Notes, and Cautions</title> 
	 <para> Use tips, notes, and cautions to highlight important information.
		The following summarizes the differences between tips, notes, and cautions:
		</para> 
	 <variablelist> 
		<varlistentry> 
		  <term>Tip</term> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Provides practical but non-essential information that is
				related to the current discussion. A tip usually describes an alternative
				method of performing a function. For example: </para> 
			 <tip> 
				<para> You can also use the <application>Menu Editor</application>
				  to create a custom menu. </para> 
			 </tip> 
		  </listitem> 
		</varlistentry> 
		<varlistentry> 
		  <term>Note</term> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Provides important information that is related to the current
				discussion but is not imperative. For example: </para> 
			 <note> 
				<para> A window can only be in one window group at a time. </para> 
			 </note> 
		  </listitem> 
		</varlistentry> 
		<varlistentry> 
		  <term>Caution</term> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Provides mandatory information that the user needs to know to
				protect the user from personal injury or from damaging hardware or software.
				For example: </para> 
			 <caution> 
				<para> Irreversible destruction can occur to data or the operating
				  system. Follow the instructions carefully. </para> 
			 </caution> 
		  </listitem> 
		</varlistentry> 
	 </variablelist> 
  </sect1> 
  <sect1 id="infodesign-19"> 
	 <title>Endnotes and Footnotes</title> 
	 <para> Use endnotes and footnotes to provide complete cross-references to
		other sources or to add comments about a discussion. Endnotes are displayed at
		the end of a chapter or book. Footnotes are displayed at the end of a page or a
		table. The stylesheet that you use usually determines the format and placement
		of endnotes and footnotes. </para> 
	 <sect2 id="infodesign-20"> 
		<title>Guidelines for Creating Endnotes and Footnotes</title> 
		<para> Use the following guidelines for creating endnotes or footnotes:
		  </para> 
		<itemizedlist> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Place the endnote or footnote reference at the end of the
				sentence, phrase, or quotation. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Use consecutive numerals that are displayed in superscript to
				indicate an endnote or footnote reference. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		  <listitem> 
			 <para> Repeat the numeral at the start of the endnote or footnote
				text. </para> 
		  </listitem> 
		</itemizedlist> 
	 </sect2> 
  </sect1> 
</chapter> 
