<chapter id="legal-issues"> 
  <title>Legal Topics</title> 
  <para>
	 This chapter provides guidelines on how to use trademarks in MATE
	 documentation.
  </para>
  <sect1 id="trademarks"> 
	 <title>Trademarks</title> 
	 <para>
		Avoid using trademarked terms in free software documentation.
	 </para>
  </sect1> 
  <sect1 id="copyrights"> 
	 <title>Copyrights</title> 
	 <para>
		You must place the copyright notice in a manner and location that gives
		reasonable notice to the claim of copyright. In MATE documentation, always use
		the front matter page for the copyright notice. See the front matter page of
		this style guide for an example of the appropriate way to assign copyrights.
	 </para>
	 <sect2> 
		<title>Use of the Copyright Word and the Copyright Symbol</title> 
		<para>
		  The front matter sections in templates for MATE documentation are set
		  up to generate both the word <emphasis>Copyright</emphasis>, and the copyright
		  symbol ©. Although the use of both the copyright word and the copyright symbol
		  together is not required in the USA and in many other countries, you should
		  include both in MATE documentation for the following reasons: 
		  <orderedlist> 
			 <listitem> 
				<para>
				  There are no formal copyright notice requirements in the Berne
				  Convention.
				</para>
			 </listitem> 
			 <listitem> 
				<para>
				  The Universal Copyright Convention (UCC) states that any
				  formality in a national law may be satisfied by placing a copyright notice
				  consisting of © [copyright date] [copyright owner]. Therefore, although the
				  notice Copyright © [copyright date] [copyright owner] might be redundant in
				  jurisdictions that are members of the Berne Convention and the UCC, this is the
				  notice that provides the most copyright coverage worldwide.
				</para>
			 </listitem> 
			 <listitem> 
				<para>
				  The use of the word <emphasis>Copyright</emphasis> spelled out is
				  also helpful in the case where the © symbol cannot be displayed. This is
				  particularly helpful when the work on which the notice is affixed is in
				  electronic form.
				</para>
			 </listitem> 
		  </orderedlist> 
		</para>
	 </sect2> 
	 <sect2> 
		<title>Copyrights for Multiple Authors</title> 
		<para>
		  Assign a general copyright to each author in the front matter page. You
		  do not need to add a separate copyright page for each section that each
		  individual author provides. To credit authors for specific contributions to
		  different parts of a book, you can add an author list as an appendix to your
		  book. See <xref linkend="authorlist"/> in this book for an example of an author
		  list as an appendix. 
		</para>
	 </sect2> 
  </sect1> 
  <sect1 id="licenses"> 
	 <title>Applying the GFDL</title> 
	 <para>
		Familiarize yourself with the 
		<ulink url="http://www.gnu.org/licenses/fdl.html"> 
		  <citetitle>GNU Free Documentation License</citetitle></ulink> (GFDL).
		All MATE documentation is published under the GFDL. A free software license
		allows you to use and modify information published under that license.
	 </para>
  </sect1> 
  <sect1 id="acknowledgements"> 
	 <title>History</title> 
	 <para>
		A history section is mandatory for all documents released under the GFDL,
		even if you are writing a new manual. You must retain history data from
		previous versions of any manual that you modify. See the <emphasis>About This
		Document</emphasis> page of this guide for an example of the appropriate way to
		record history information.
	 </para>
  </sect1> 
  <sect1> 
	 <title>Acknowledgements</title> 
	 <para>
		You only need to include a section for acknowledgements if you have
		acknowledgement data. You must retain acknowledgements from any GFDL-licensed
		documentation from which you draw information, in an Acknowledgements section.
		Under the terms of the GFDL, you must also include copyrights in your manual
		for any GFDL-licensed documentation from which you draw information. However,
		in the context of the MATE project, you can contact copyright holders for
		source documentation and ask if they are willing to waive their copyrights in
		the manual that you are writing. If authors of source documentation do waive
		their copyrights for your manual, you must still acknowledge your sources in
		the Acknowledgements section. 
	 </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter> 
