<chapter id="screenshots"> 
  <title>Use of Screenshots</title> 
  <para> This chapter provides guidelines for creating and using screenshots in
	 MATE documentation. </para> 
  <sect1 id="screenshot-1"> 
	 <title>Default Settings</title> 
	 <para> As far as possible, use the default settings for the MATE Desktop
		when you take a screenshot. Include the window frame when you take a screenshot
		of a window. </para> 
  </sect1> 
  <sect1 id="screenshot-3"> 
	 <title> Required Formats</title> 
	 <para> For documentation that is for online display, you must use PNG
		format for screenshots. </para> 
  </sect1> 
  <sect1 id="screenshot-4"> 
	 <title> Image Width</title> 
	 <para> The maximum image width is 510 pixels. At this width, images fit on
		a printed page. You might need to scale down the image before you add any
		callouts, to ensure that the total width of the image is less than 510 pixels.
		You can use <application>GIMP</application> to scale images before you add
		callouts. To scale an image in <application>GIMP</application>, right-click on
		the image, then choose 
		<menuchoice> 
		  <guimenu>Image</guimenu> 
		  <guimenuitem>Scale image</guimenuitem> 
		</menuchoice>. </para> 
  </sect1> 
  <sect1 id="screenshot-7"> 
	 <title> Special Graphic Effects</title> 
	 <para> Do not use drop-shadow or any other special graphic effects on
		screenshots. Every component of information design, whether textual or visual,
		should play a role in communicating concepts to the user. If a component does
		not convey a concept, then the component adds to the processing burden for the
		user without bringing any extra understanding. Essentially, decorative
		components reduce communication effectiveness. </para> 
	 <para> Avoid special graphic effects for the following reasons: </para> 
	 <itemizedlist> 
		<listitem> 
		  <para> Any non-essential visual or textual information can distract a
			 user, or even confuse a user. </para> 
		</listitem> 
		<listitem> 
		  <para> Screenshots should appear as close as possible to what the user
			 really sees on-screen. There are no drop-shadows around windows on-screen.
			 </para> 
		</listitem> 
		<listitem> 
		  <para> Drop-shadows as pure decoration please some people. Others might
			 see such decoration as an attempt to glamorize a dull topic. </para> 
		</listitem> 
		<listitem> 
		  <para> Many icons use drop-shadows. You might want
			 to include screenshots of these icons in the documentation. If you add
			 drop-shadows to your application screenshots, you risk devaluing drop-shadows
			 on icons. Also, the use of drop-shadows for different purposes can confuse the
			 user. </para> 
		</listitem> 
	 </itemizedlist> 
  </sect1> 
  <sect1 id="screenshot-5"> 
	 <title> Using Callouts</title> 
	 <para> This section discusses the use of callouts with screenshots. </para>
	 
	 <sect2> 
		<title>When to Use Callouts</title> 
		<para> Use callouts to graphically identify key features. Do not use
		  callouts to give instructions such as "Click here to close the window".
		  Instead, identify the feature and give the instructions in text. The following
		  figure shows a screenshot that uses callouts to graphically identify key
		  features. 
		  <figure id="screenshot-FIG-1"> 
			 <title>Sample Screenshot with Callouts</title> 
			 <mediaobject> 
				<imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/sample_anno_panel.png"
				  format="PNG"/> 
				</imageobject> 
				<textobject> 
				  <phrase>Sample screenshot with callouts.</phrase> 
				</textobject> 
			 </mediaobject> 
		  </figure> </para> 
	 </sect2> 
	 <sect2> 
		<title>Callout Text </title> 
		<para> Use the <application>GIMP</application> <application>Dynamic
		  Text</application> plugin to create callout text. The features of the
		  <application>Dynamic Text</application> plugin make localization of the callout
		  text easier. For example, a translator can double-click on callout text to open
		  the 
		  <guilabel>Dynamic Text</guilabel> dialog, then paste in the translated
		  text. For more information on the <application>Dynamic Text</application>
		  plugin, see the entry in the 
		  <ulink url="http://registry.gimp.org/plugin?id=337">GIMP Plugin
			 Registry</ulink>. </para> 
		<para> Ensure that you leave sufficient space around callout text to
		  allow for the expansion of the text after translation. </para> 
		<para> Use sentence capitalization rules in the callout text. Terms that
		  normally take initial capitals are exceptions to this rule. </para> 
	 </sect2> 
	 <sect2> 
		<title> Callout Lines</title> 
		<para> Use straight horizontal lines and vertical lines only. Do not draw
		  lines at an oblique angle to the screenshot. Due to the limitations of raster
		  formats such as PNG, lines drawn at an oblique angle to the screenshot appear
		  jagged. Beware that straight callout lines might not be very clear if they are
		  parallel and close to lines in the window display that represent edges of
		  window elements. </para> 
		<para> Keep callout lines as simple as possible. Try to restrict the
		  callout line to one straight line. Where possible, do not create a
		  perpendicular angle on the callout line that leads into the text. </para> 
		<para> Do not create callout lines that fold back on themselves. If a
		  callout line must be more complex than one straight line, ensure that the
		  callout flows in one direction. The following figure is an example of callout
		  lines <emphasis>not</emphasis> flowing in one direction: 
		  <figure id="screenshot-FIG-2"> 
			 <title>Callout Lines Flowing in More Than One Direction</title> 
			 <mediaobject> 
				<imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/callout_notflow.png"
				  format="PNG"/> 
				</imageobject> 
				<textobject> 
				  <phrase>Sample of callout lines flowing in more than one
					 direction.</phrase> 
				</textobject> 
			 </mediaobject> 
		  </figure> </para> 
		<para> Use the pencil tool to draw callout lines. Do not use the
		  <application>Gfig</application> plugin. The pencil tool is easier to use and
		  gives you more precise, close control. When you use the
		  <application>Gfig</application> plugin, you might have difficulty in ensuring
		  that the lines are drawn at consistent angles to the image. </para> 
	 </sect2> 
  </sect1> 
  <sect1 id="screenshot-9"> 
	 <title>Text Equivalents for Screenshots</title> 
	 <para> For information about writing text equivalents for graphics, see
		<xref linkend="accessibility"/>. </para> 
  </sect1> 
  <sect1 id="screenshot-10"> 
	 <title>When to Use Screenshots</title> 
	 <para> For guidelines about when to use screenshots in online Help and
		printed manuals, see <xref linkend="infodesign"/>. </para> 
  </sect1> 
</chapter> 
