<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect3 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
                  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" []>

	  <sect3 id="calloutscreenshots">
		<title>Creating Screenshots With Callouts</title>
	 <para>
You can download a sample screenshot with callouts, <ulink url="sample_anno_panel.xcf">sample_anno_panel.xcf</ulink>. This file is in the native format of GIMP, XCF. To create a screenshot and all callouts to the screenshot, follow these steps:</para> 
	 <orderedlist> 
		<listitem>
		  <para>Start <application>GIMP</application>.</para>
		</listitem> 
		<listitem>
		  <para>Choose 
			 <menuchoice>
				<guimenu>File</guimenu>
				<guisubmenu>Acquire</guisubmenu>
				<guimenuitem>Screenshot</guimenuitem>
			 </menuchoice>. A 
			 <guilabel>Screen Shot</guilabel> dialog is displayed. </para>
		</listitem> 
		<listitem>
		  <para>Select the options that you require in the 
			 <guilabel>Screen Shot</guilabel> dialog, then click 
			 <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. <application>GIMP</application> takes the
			 screenshot, and displays the screenshot.</para>
		</listitem> 
		<listitem>
		  <para>Create space on the image in which to add the callouts. To do
			 this, right-click on the image, then choose 
			 <menuchoice>
				<guimenu>Image</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Canvas Size</guimenuitem>
			 </menuchoice>. A 
			 <guilabel>Set Canvas Size</guilabel> dialog is displayed. Specify the
			 new size of the image in the upper part of this dialog. Use the lower part of
			 the dialog to position the screenshot in the image.</para> 
		  <para>Alternatively, you can create a large new image, then paste in
			 the screenshot. When you are finished you can use the 
			 <guilabel>Crop</guilabel> tool to resize the image. </para>
		</listitem> 
		<listitem>
		  <para>Save the file in XCF format. XCF is the native format of 
			 <application>GIMP</application> and allows you to use complex
			 graphical features such as layers.</para>
		</listitem> 
		<listitem>
		  <para>When your screenshot is localized, the localizer might cut out the 
			 screenshot in the original language, and paste in the screenshot in 
			 the new language. A mark that indicates the location of the screenshot 
			 might be helpful in this case.</para>
		  <para>Create the mark in a new layer. To create a new layer,
			 right-click on the image, then choose 
			 <menuchoice>
				<guimenu>Layers</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Layers, Channels &amp; Paths</guimenuitem>
			 </menuchoice>. The 
			 <guilabel>Layers, Channels &amp; Paths</guilabel> dialog is
			 displayed. Click on the 
			 <guibutton>New Layer</guibutton> button at the bottom left of the
			 dialog. Name the layer <emphasis>Top left corner of image</emphasis>. </para> 
		  <para> Use the 
			 <guilabel>Pencil</guilabel> tool to draw a right angle around the top left 
			 corner of the image.  Format the lines as follows:</para> 
		  <itemizedlist> 
			 <listitem>
				<para>Foreground colour: Green (Hex triplet: #00ff00)</para>
			 </listitem> 
		  </itemizedlist>
 		</listitem>  
		<listitem>
		  <para>Create a new layer for the callout lines. Name the layer 
<emphasis>Callout lines</emphasis>. </para> 
		  <para> Use the 
			 <guilabel>Pencil</guilabel> tool to draw the callout lines. To keep
			 the lines straight, click to start drawing the line, then press-and-hold 
			 <keycap>Shift</keycap>. Format the lines as follows:</para> 
		  <itemizedlist> 
			 <listitem>
				<para>Brush: pixel (1 x 1 square)</para>
			 </listitem> 
			 <listitem>
				<para>Foreground colour: Black (Hex triplet: #000000)</para>
			 </listitem> 
		  </itemizedlist> 
		  <para>Use straight horizontal and vertical lines only.</para> 
		</listitem> 
		<listitem>
		  <para>Use the dynamic text plugin to create the callout text. To access
			 the Dynamic Text plugin, right-click on an image, then choose 
			 <menuchoice>
				<guimenu>Filters</guimenu>
				<guisubmenu>Render</guisubmenu>
				<guimenuitem>Dynamic Text</guimenuitem>
			 </menuchoice>. This creates a new layer for each text item. Format
			 the text as follows: </para> 
		  <itemizedlist> 
			 <listitem>
				<para>helvetica(adobe)</para>
			 </listitem> 
			 <listitem>
				<para>medium</para>
			 </listitem> 
			 <listitem>
				<para>11-point</para>
			 </listitem> 
			 <listitem>
				<para>anti-aliased</para>
			 </listitem> 
		  </itemizedlist> 
		  <para>Rename the layers so that the name of the layer matches the text
			 that appears in the callout. Prefix each layer name with <emphasis>Text:
			 </emphasis>. </para>
		</listitem> 
		<listitem>
		  <para>Save the image as PNG (right-click on the image and choose 
			 <menuchoice>
				<guimenu>File</guimenu>
				<guimenuitem>Save As</guimenuitem>
			 </menuchoice>). An 
			 <guilabel>Export File</guilabel> dialog is displayed. This warns that
			 you are about to flatten the layers in the image. Click on the 
			 <guibutton>Export</guibutton> button. A 
			 <guilabel>Save As PNG</guilabel> dialog is displayed. Deselect the 
			 <guilabel>Save background color</guilabel> option. <emphasis>Ensure
			 that you do not overwrite the XCF file!</emphasis></para>
		</listitem> 
	 </orderedlist> 
  </sect3>
