<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
                  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" []>
<!-- ################# Teamwork ############### -->

  <sect1 id="teamwork">
    <title>Teamwork</title>  <!-- ####### Teamwork | Working With The
GDP Team ####### -->

    <sect2 id="teamworkgdp">
      <title>Working with the GDP Team</title>
      <para>
        The GDP team is a valuable resource for any documentation
        author.  GDP members can answer most questions documentation
        authors have during the course of their work. It is also
        important to make sure you are not duplicating work of other
        GDP members by sending an email to <email>mate-doc-list@mate.org</email>
		and verify no one is working on the documentation for the 
		application you are working on.  It is also a good idea to send an 
		email to the application's maintainer so the maintainer knows 
		you want to work on the documentation for their program. 
<!--
		visiting the <citetitle>GDP Documentation
        Status Table</citetitle> (<ulink
        url="http://www.mate.org/gdp/doctable/"
        type="http">http://www.mate.org/gdp/doctable/</ulink>) and
        assigning a documentation item to yourself.  This table also
        provides a forum for making suggestions and announcements for
        each documentation item.  
-->		
		The best way to get in touch with
        GDP members is on the #docs IRC channel at irc.mate.org or
        else by emailing the <ulink type="http"
        url="http://mail.mate.org/mailman/listinfo/mate-doc-list/">
        <citetitle>mate-doc-list mailing list</citetitle></ulink>.
      </para>
      <para>
        After an author has finished a document (or even a draft
        version of the document), it is a good idea to ask a member of
        the GDP team to read the document, checking it for grammar,
        proper DocBook markup, and clarity.  One may typically find
        another author to do this by either asking on the #docs IRC
        channel at irc.mate.org or by emailing the <ulink type="http"
        url="http://mail.mate.org/mailman/listinfo/mate-doc-list/">
        <citetitle>mate-doc-list mailing list</citetitle></ulink>.
      </para>
    </sect2>

<!-- ####### Teamwork | Working With Developers ####### -->

    <sect2 id="teamworkdevelopers">
      <title>Working with Developers</title>
      <para>
        Writing documentation typically involves a certain amount of
        interaction with the developers of MATE or the application
        which is being documented.  Often a document author will need
        to ask the developer technical questions during the course of
        writing a document. After the document is finished, it is a good
        idea to ask the developer to read the document to make sure it
        is technically correct.  The documentation author should also
        make sure that the application author correctly binds and
        packages the documentation with the application.
      </para>
    </sect2>

<!-- ####### Teamwork | Working With Users #######

    <sect2 id="teamworkusers">
      <title>Working With Users</title>
      <para>
        Some document authors may wish to get feedback on their
        documents directly from users.  This may be done by ...
      </para>
    </sect2>-->
  </sect1>
