<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?><!-- -*- indent-tabs-mode: nil -*- -->

<chapter id="core-tech">
  <title>Core Technologies</title>

<section id="graphics">
  <title>Graphical Interfaces</title>

  <para>Most applications will need to provide a graphical interface to
  interact with users.  Graphical interfaces can create an intuitive and
  discoverable medium for people to interact with software, and users expect
  applications to provide usable and attractive user interfaces.</para>

  <para>The MATE Platform features sophisticated graphics and user interface
  technology, from standard user interface controls to an API for drawing
  high-quality graphics to the screen.  Using the graphics technologies in
  MATE allows you to create applications that are consistent, intuitive,
  and aesthetically pleasing.</para>

  <figure>
    <title>Layered Look at Graphics Libraries</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="figures/graphics.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <section id="gtk">
    <title>GTK+</title>

    <para>GTK+ is the primary library used to construct user interfaces
    in MATE.  It provides all the user interface controls, or widgets,
    used in a common graphical application.  Its modern, object-oriented
    API allows you to construct attractive and sophisticated user
    interfaces without dealing with the low-level details of drawing and
    device interaction.</para>

    <para>In addition to basic widgets, such as buttons, check boxes,
    and text entries, GTK+ also provides powerful Model-View-Controller
    (MVC) APIs for tree views, multi-line text fields, and menu and
    toolbar actions.</para>

    <para>Widgets in GTK+ are placed on windows using a box-packing model.
    Programmers specify only how to pack widgets together in container
    boxes, rather than position them directly with absolute coordinates.
    GTK+ ensures that windows are sized correctly to fit their contents,
    and it automatically handles window resizing.</para>

    <para>Because GTK+ offers a flexible API, developing additional widgets
    for use in GTK+ applications is easy.  A number of third-party libraries
    exist which provide additional widgets, and many developers have created
    custom, special-purpose widgets for their applications.</para>

    <para>GTK+ handles the difficult details of user interfaces and user
    interaction, and provides a simple yet powerful API which allows you
    to focus on the details of your application.  Applications developed
    with GTK+ will automatically follow the user's theme and font settings,
    will interact properly with accessibility technologies, and will behave
    as users expect.</para>

    <para>For more information on GTK+, see the
    <ulink url="http://library.mate.org/devel/gtk/stable/">GTK+ Reference
    Manual</ulink> or visit
    <ulink url="http://gtk.org/">the GTK+ web site</ulink>.</para>
  </section> <!-- gtk -->

  <section id="libglade">
    <title>Libglade</title>
    <note><para><note><para>Note that Libglade has been deprecated in favor of
    <ulink url="http://library.mate.org/devel/gtk/stable/GtkBuilder.html">GtkBuilder</ulink>.
    Newly written code should use GtkBuilder instead.</para></note></para></note>

    <para>Libglade is a library for constructing user interfaces dynamically
    from XML descriptions.  You can use a graphical interface builder like
    <application>Glade</application> to construct your user interface,
    and then import the interface description into your application.  This
    makes it easy to construct complex layouts and adjust layout details.</para>

    <para>Libglade allows programmers to focus their code on the logic of
    their applications, keeping it uncluttered by the actual construction
    of the interface.  Graphical interface builders also make it easy for
    dedicated interface designers to construct the interfaces without having
    to know how to program.</para>

    <para>For more information on Libglade, see the <ulink
    url="http://library.mate.org/devel/libglade/stable/">Libglade
    Reference Manual</ulink>.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="pango">
    <title>Pango</title>

    <para>Pango is the core text and font handling library in the MATE
    platform.  It is responsible for laying out and rendering text, and
    is used throughout GTK+.<footnote>
    <para>The Pango layout engine can be used with different font
    backends and drawing backends.  On most MATE systems, Pango
    will use FreeType, fontconfig, and Cairo to access fonts and
    render text.  On other systems, Pango will use the native font
    systems, such as Uniscribe on Microsoft Windows and ATSUI on
    MacOS</para></footnote></para>
 
    <para>Pango has extensive support for the various writing systems
    used throughout the world.  Many of the writing systems used for
    languages have complex rules for laying out glyphs and composing
    characters.  With Pango, nearly all languages can be written and
    displayed correctly, allowing users everywhere to view text in their
    native languages.  Pango support for multiple writing systems is
    automatic; application developers do not have to write any special
    code to support other languages.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Displaying Multiple Languages With Pango</title>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="figures/pango.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject><para>Screenshot of the <application>gedit</application>
          text editor displaying phrases from multiple languages and writing
          systems.</para></textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>

    <para>Pango supports the text styling used in typical documents
    and interfaces, including italics, font weights, and underlines.
    Pango uses a simple XML-like vocabulary called PangoMarkup which
    enables you to set font size, color, styles, and other text
    attributes.  Using PangoMarkup, you can specify inline styles
    without manually iterating over text blocks.  PangoMarkup can
    be used directly from GTK+, enabling you to style text in your
    graphical interfaces easily.</para>

    <para>You should use Pango directly whenever you need to lay
    text out on the screen or on a different medium.  Using Pango
    will allow your text layout to work seamlessly with GTK+ and
    the rest of the MATE platform.  It will help you create
    portable code, and most importantly, it will ensure that your
    application can render text correctly in hundreds of different
    languages.</para>

    <para>For more information on Pango, see the
    <ulink url="http://library.mate.org/devel/pango/stable/">Pango
    Reference Manual</ulink>.</para>
  </section> <!-- pango -->

  <section id="gdk">
    <title>GDK</title>

    <para>GDK is the low-level library used by GTK+ to interact with the
    system for graphics and input devices.  Although you will rarely use
    GDK directly in application code, it contains all the necessary
    functionality to draw objects and text to the screen and to interact
    with the user with various input devices.<footnote>
    <para>GDK runs on a number of different platforms, including the X Window
    System, Microsoft Windows, DirectFB, and Quartz.  On any platform, GDK
    provides the same consistent API, allowing GTK+ and GTK+ applications to
    run unmodified.</para></footnote></para>

    <para>GDK features a graphics context and drawing primitives that are
    suitable for drawing simple objects and rendering images on the screen.
    Since a more extensive drawing system is provided by Cairo, GDK provides
    hooks to use Cairo contexts within GDK.</para>

    <para>GDK enables you to access events from keyboards, mice, and other
    input devices, rather than connect to the high-level signals used in
    GTK+.  GDK also provides low-level routines to access drag and drop
    and clipboard data from the system.  When implementing custom controls,
    you may need to access these features to implement proper user interaction
    behavior.</para>

    <para>GDK provides other functionality which is needed to implement
    a complete graphical toolkit like GTK+.  Since GDK acts as a platform
    abstraction, allowing GTK+ to run under multiple environments, it
    provides an API for all of the system functionality needed by GTK+.
    This includes information about multi-head displays, resolution and
    color depth, colormaps, and cursors.</para>

    <para>You should use GDK whenever you need low-level access to the
    underlying windowing system, including low-level access to events,
    windows, and the clipboard.  Using GDK for these tasks ensures that
    your code is portable and integrates with the rest of your GTK+ code.
    The simple drawing routines in GDK should generally not be used.
    Instead, you should use the extensive functionality provide by
    Cairo.</para>

    <para>For more information on GDK, see the
    <ulink url="http://library.mate.org/devel/gdk/stable/">GDK Reference
    Manual</ulink>.</para>
  </section> <!-- gdk -->

  <section id="cairo">
    <title>Cairo</title>

    <para>Cairo is a 2D graphics library featuring a sophisticated API for
    drawing vector graphics, compositing images, and rendering anti-aliased
    text.  Cairo provides support for multiple output devices, including the
    X Window System, Microsoft Windows, and image buffers, allowing you to
    write platform-independent code to draw graphics on different media.</para>

    <para>The Cairo drawing model is similar to those provided by PostScript
    and PDF.  The Cairo API provides such drawing operations as stroking and
    filling cubic Bézier splines, compositing images, and performing affine
    transformations.  These vector operations allow for rich, anti-aliased
    graphics without using expensive pixel-based drawing in your application
    code.</para>

    <para>Cairo's rich drawing model allows for high-quality rendering to
    multiple media.  The same API can be used to create stunning on-screen
    graphics and text, to render images, or create crisp output suitable
    for printing.</para>

    <para>You should use Cairo whenever you need to draw graphics in your
    application beyond the widgets provided by GTK+.  Much of the drawing
    inside GTK+ is done using Cairo.  Using Cairo for your custom drawing
    will allow your application to have high-quality, anti-aliased, and
    resolution-independent graphics.</para>

    <para>For more information on Cairo, see <ulink
    url="http://www.cairographics.org/manual/">Cairo: A Vector Graphics
    Library</ulink>.</para>
  </section> <!-- cairo -->
</section> <!-- graphics -->

<section id="gio">
  <title>Virtual File System</title>

  <para>GIO, a part of GLib, is the core library used for file and folder
  operations in MATE applications.  GIO provides a unified file system
  abstraction layer with pluggable backends.  In MATE, the GVFS library
  provides a GIO backend implementing multiple network and local protocols.
  Using GIO with GVFS allows your application to work with files on remote
  machines as easily as local files.</para>
  
  <para>GIO can provide extensive information about files and folders, including
  the MIME type and icon of a file and which applications can be used to open
  a file.  Since the GVFS uses the standard from <ulink
  url="http://www.freedesktop.org/">freedesktop.org</ulink> to determine
  file types and associations, it works correctly on different free desktop
  environments, helping independent software developers create
  software that can be run in different environments.</para>

  <para>GIO is used throughout the MATE desktop.  The file manager,
  <application>Caja</application>, uses GIO to display folders on local
  and remote systems.  For the user, this means that network servers act just
  like local folders: They can drag and drop files between them, view the files'
  properties, and open the file with an application.  Using GIO will allow your
  application to open all the files that users can access on their desktop.</para>

  <para>For more information on GIO, see the <ulink
  url="http://library.mate.org/devel/gio/stable/">GIO Reference Manual</ulink>.</para>

  <anchor id="mate-vfs"/>

  <para>In previous versions of MATE, the MateVFS library was used for
  access to files and folders.  While MateVFS provided many of the same
  features, including transparent access to remote folders, it had a number
  of limitations which have been addressed in GIO.  MateVFS is deprecated
  and should not be used in newly written code, although it will continue
  to be supported throughout the MATE 2 lifetime.  For information on
  MateVFS, see <ulink
  url="http://library.mate.org/devel/mate-vfs-2.0/stable/">MateVFS -
  Filesystem Abstraction Library</ulink>.</para>
</section> <!-- gio -->

<section id="mateconf">
  <title>Configuration and Lockdown</title>

  <para>MateConf is the system for storing and retrieving configuration settings
  in MATE.  MateConf consists of two parts: a client library for accessing
  settings, and a session daemon which is responsible for the details of
  storing and retrieving those settings.  Using a daemon allows MateConf to
  use different storage backends, validate input, and provide simultaneous
  access to different applications.</para>

  <para>Settings stored in MateConf are stored and retrieved using a unique
  key, or identifier string.  Keys use a simple hierarchical namespace to
  avoid collision among settings for applications and the desktop.  You
  can provide a schema file to detail your configuration keys.  This allows
  MateConf to validate the type of the input, and to show localized documentation
  about the key.  This helps systems administrators, who can set multiple
  settings at once without having to navigate preference dialogs.</para>

  <para>MateConf can look up settings from different settings at once, typically
  from different locations on the file system.  By having appropriate system
  sources configured, MateConf enables systems administrators to provide both
  default and mandatory settings for all users.  Tools such as MATE's
  <application>Configuration Editor</application> and
  <application>Sabayon</application> make it easy to deploy fully
  configured systems using MateConf.</para>

  <para>The MateConf client library provides notifications of changes to
  settings, making it easy to provide instant-apply settings in your
  application, regardless if settings are changed from within your
  application or using another tool.  Setting the value of a key will
  notify all interested applications, allowing desktop-wide and other
  cross-application settings to work instantly and effortlessly.</para>

  <para>MateConf makes it easy to lock down systems by setting particular
  keys read-only, preventing users from changing their values.  In
  addition, MATE provides a number of high-level keys that can be used
  to disable actions such as saving to disk and changing the panel layout.
  Tools such as <application>Pessulus</application> make it easy for
  administrators to find and lock down important keys.</para>

  <para>You should use MateConf to store all user preferences in your
  application.  Using MateConf will make it easy to provide instant-apply
  preferences, and it will make your settings accessible to systems
  administrators and configuration and backup tools.</para>

  <para>For more information on MateConf, see the <ulink
  url="http://library.mate.org/devel/mateconf/stable/">MateConf
  Reference Manual</ulink>.</para>
</section> <!-- mateconf -->

<section id="i18n">
  <title>Internationalization</title>
  <para>The MATE Desktop and Developer Platform provides full support for
  internationalizing and localizing applications.  Internationalization is
  the process of ensuring your application can be localized, including
  marking all strings for translations, using numbers and format strings
  correctly, and making adjustments for variations in conventions for
  times and dates, units, and formatting.</para>

  <para>MATE uses the standard gettext and related routines for accessing
  localizations.  Support for localization using gettext is built into
  every component of the MATE platform.  Your source code can be scanned
  for specially-marked tools by automated tools.  Those strings are then
  placed in PO files to allow translators to track their translations.
  Using gettext, you can easily and efficiently access translated versions
  of all user-visible strings in your application from translation domains
  installed along with your application.</para>

  <para>These translation domains can be created using PO files, which
  can be used by translators to track string changes and update their
  translations accordingly.  MATE ships with intltool, a tool for
  managing translations in PO files.  Using intltool, translators can
  use PO files to translate not only the strings in your application,
  but also other types of files that you use, such as MateConf schema
  files, desktop entry files, and XML files.</para>

  <para>MATE also provides the xml2po tool as part of the mate-doc-utils
  package.  This tool allows translators to use PO files to create
  translated versions of documentation written in various XML formats,
  including XHTML and DocBook.</para>

  <para>Internationalization involves more than just allowing strings
  to be translated, and MATE supports your application development
  at every step of the process.  GTK+ will automatically adjust its
  presentation for languages that are read right-to-left, and Pango
  has complete support for rendering bidirectional text and text in
  various different writing systems. GTK+ supports multiple input
  methods, allowing users from all language to input text efficiently
  with their keyboards.  The entire MATE platform uses the UTF-8
  encoding of Unicode natively, providing access to the characters
  and writing systems of the entire world.</para>

  <figure>
    <title><application>Gnumeric</application> in Multiple Languages</title>
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata format="PNG" fileref="figures/i18n.png"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject><para>Screenshots of the <application>Gnumeric</application>
        spreadsheet application running in Hebrew, Japanese, and Serbian.</para>
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </figure>

  <para>Internationalizing your application helps make it available
  to many more users across the world.  While skilled translators
  must provide translations for any language, programmers must ensure
  the application is properly internationalized before it can be fully
  localized.</para>

  <!-- FIXME: where is danilo's awesome guide? -->
  <para>For more information on internationalization in MATE, see <ulink
  url="http://www.mate.org/~malcolm/i18n/">Internationalizing MATE
  Applications</ulink>.</para>
</section> <!-- i18n -->

<section id="a11y">
  <title>Accessibility</title>

  <para>Accessibility is the process of ensuring your application can be
  used by people with various disabilities.  Disabilities come in many forms:
  visual impairments, movement impairments, hearing impairments, cognitive
  and language impairments, and seizure disorders.  Many people have some
  sort of disability, and making your application accessibility will allow
  more people to use your application effectively.</para>

  <para>MATE provides support for accessibility devices using the ATK
  framework.  This framework defines a set of interfaces to which graphical
  interface components adhere.  This allows, for instance, screen readers
  to read the text of an interface and interact with its controls.  ATK
  support is built into GTK+ and the rest of the MATE platform using the
  GAIL library, so any application using GTK+ will have reasonable
  accessibility support for free.</para>

  <para>Nonetheless, you should be aware of accessibility issues when
  when developing your applications.  Although GTK+ interfaces provide
  reasonable accessibility by default, you can often improve how well
  your program behaves with accessibility tools by providing additional
  information to ATK.  If you develop custom widgets, you should ensure
  that they expose their properties to ATK.  You should also avoid using
  sound, graphics, or color as the sole means of conveying information
  to the user.</para>

  <para>The MATE desktop ships with a number of accessibility tools
  which enable users with disabilities to take full advantage of their
  desktop and applications.  Applications that fully implement ATK will
  be able to work with the accessibility tools.  MATE's accessibility
  tools include a screen reader, a screen magnifier, an on-screen
  keyboard, and <application>Dasher</application>, an innovative
  predictive text entry tool.</para>

  <para>For extensive recommendations on accessibility, see <ulink
  url="http://developer.mate.org/projects/gap/guide/gad/index.html">MATE
  Accessibility for Developers</ulink>.  See also <ulink
  url="http://library.mate.org/devel/atk/stable/">ATK -
  Accessibility Toolkit</ulink> and the <ulink
  url="http://library.mate.org/devel/gail-libgail-util/stable/">GAIL
  Reference Manual</ulink>.</para>
</section> <!-- a11y -->

<section id="multimedia">
  <title>Multimedia</title>

  <para>GStreamer is a powerful multimedia library for playing, creating,
  and manipulating sound, video, and other media.  You can use GStreamer
  to provide sound and video playback, record input from multiple sources,
  and edit multimedia content.  GStreamer supports encoding and decoding
  numerous formats by default, and support for additional formats can be
  added with plug-ins.</para>

  <para>GStreamer provides a flexible architecture wherein media is
  processed through a pipeline of elements.  Each element may apply
  filters to the content, such as encoding or decoding, combining
  multiple sources, or transforming the multimedia content.  This
  architecture allows for an arbitrary arrangement of elements,
  so that you can accomplish virtually any effect using GStreamer.
  Furthermore, GStreamer is designed to have low overhead, so it
  can be used in applications with high demands on latency.</para>

  <para>While GStreamer provides a powerful API for manipulating
  multimedia, it also provides convenient routines for simple
  playback.  GStreamer can automatically construct a pipeline to
  read and playback files in any supported format, allowing you
  to use sound and video in your application easily.</para>

  <para>The GStreamer architecture allows plugins to add encoders,
  decoders, and all sorts of content filters.  Third-party developers
  can provide GStreamer plugins which will be automatically available
  to other applications using GStreamer.  Plugins can provide support
  for other multimedia formats or provide additional functionality
  and effects.</para>

  <para>You should use GStreamer whenever you need to read or play
  multimedia content in your application, or if your application
  needs to manipulate sound or video.  Using GStreamer makes your
  application development easy, and it provides you well-tested
  elements for many of your needs.</para>

  <para>For comprehensive information on GStreamer, see <ulink
  url="http://gstreamer.freedesktop.org/data/doc/gstreamer/head/manual/html/index.html">The
  GStreamer Application Development Manual</ulink>, <ulink
  url="http://gstreamer.freedesktop.org/data/doc/gstreamer/head/gstreamer/html/">The
  GStreamer 0.10 Core Reference Manual</ulink>, and <ulink
  url="http://gstreamer.freedesktop.org/documentation/">the
  GStreamer documentation page</ulink>.</para>
</section> <!-- multimedia -->

<section id="printing">
  <title>Printing</title>

  <para>Most applications need to provide support for printing.  Users expect
  to be able to print the contents they can view on-screen.  The MATE platform
  provides libraries to help you add support for high-quality printing to your
  application.</para>

  <section id="mateprint">
    <title>MATE Print</title>

    <note><para>Note that this section is outdated and that libmateprint and
    libmateprintui have been deprecated in favor of <ulink
    url="http://library.mate.org/devel/gtk/stable/Printing.html">GtkPrint</ulink>.
    Printing has been integrated directly into GTK+ 2.10 and later versions,
    providing a cross-platform print API that all applications can use.
    API and ABI stability guarantees ensures that Mateprint will continue to
    be functional and supported throughout the MATE 2 lifecycle.</para></note>

    <para>The MATE print framework consists of two libraries which help
    you provide high-quality printing with a consistent interface in your
    application.  At the core of the printing framework is libmateprint,
    a library for creating PostScript output to send to printers.  On top
    of that is libmateprintui, which provides standard print controls for
    your user interface.</para>

    <para>The libmateprint library implements the PostScript imaging model,
    which is used by most printers.  Printers which do not support PostScript
    can still be supported through CUPS, described below.  In addition to the
    standard PostScript imaging, libmateprint also features alpha channel
    support and anti-aliasing.</para>

    <para>The libmateprintui library provides a standard print dialog, a print
    preview dialog, and various other controls and functionality required to
    build printing into an intuitive user interface.  The MATE print framework
    handles the details of locating printers and spooling print jobs, and also
    provides PostScript and PDF export directly in the print dialog.</para>

    <para>You should use libmateprint whenever you need to render content to
    PostScript for printing.  You should use libmateprintui to construct your
    printing user interface, even if your rendered output comes from another
    source.  Using the MATE print framework provides your users a consistent
    user interface with the features they expect of printing appliations.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="cups">
    <title>CUPS</title>

    <para>On most MATE systems, CUPS (Common UNIX Printing System) acts as
    the low-level printing system.  CUPS provides a modern, feature-rich
    architecture for printer discovery, printer option access, and spooling
    print jobs to different types of printers.</para>

    <para>CUPS provides a set of utilities for automatically discovering
    printers locally and on the network.  This allows users not only to see
    all available printers, but to use different types of printers without
    manual configuration.</para>

    <para>CUPS provides a unified interface for printing, regardless of the
    location or type of the printer.  Multiple print protocols are handled
    seamlessly by CUPS by automatically applying filters to content sent to
    the printers.  Applications can simply provide PostScript output, and
    CUPS will automatically convert it for printers that do not support
    PostScript natively.</para>

    <para>CUPS also provides printer configuration options in the form of
    PostScript Printer Description (PPD) files.  PPD configurations allow
    applications to expose the capabilities of individual printers to the
    users with a consistent user interface.  For instance, PPD allows you
    to detect whether a printer can collate and staple print jobs, and to
    provide an option in your user interface.</para>

    <para>In most cases, you will not need to interface directly with CUPS
    in your applications.  By using the MATE print framework, you have
    access to the power and flexibility of CUPS automatically.  Having CUPS
    underneath means a better user experience with less programming.</para>
  </section>
</section> <!-- printing -->

</chapter>
