<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?><!-- -*- indent-tabs-mode: nil -*- -->

<chapter id="intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>MATE is a powerful but simple desktop environment with a strong focus
  on usability, accessibility, and internationalization.  MATE is designed to
  be usable by everybody, regardless of technical expertise, disabilitites, or
  native language.  MATE makes it easy for people to use their computers.</para>

  <para>MATE provides a comprehensive developer platform that allow developers
  to create professional software that is easy to use and aesthetically pleasing.
  This document provides a high-level overview of the MATE platform along with
  links to detailed documentation on each part of the platform.</para>

<section id="who-should-read">
  <title>Who Should Read This Document</title>

  <para>You should read this document if you want to create software using the
  MATE platform.  Developing with the MATE platform will help you create
  consistent applications that integrate well into the user's desktop.  This
  guide will introduce you to the various components of the platform, so you
  know which libraries can accomplish which tasks.  This guide links to
  additional detailed documentation, so you can explore each component of
  the platform in more depth.</para>

  <para>This guide will also be useful if you are picking a development
  platform for your software project.  It will provide an overview how you
  can use the MATE platform to build useful software.</para>

  <para>This guide also describes ways of extending the MATE desktop with
  plugins, panel applets, and other useful tools.  If you want to develop
  additional functionality to plug into the MATE desktop, you should read
  this guide, particularly <xref linkend="desktop-tech"/>.</para>

  <para>If you have existing software that you want to port to the MATE
  platform, you should see the online <ulink
  url="http://live.mate.org/GuideForISVs">Guide For ISVs</ulink> in
  addition to this guide.</para>
</section>

<section id="mate-family">
  <title>The MATE Family</title>

  <para>MATE is a global effort, with many contributors all over the world.
  MATE is a success because of its contributors and users.  This section
  lists the web sites and conferences where you can learn more about MATE,
  as well as other organizations that work with MATE.</para>

  <variablelist>
    <title>Web Sites</title>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><ulink url="http://www.mate.org/">www.mate.org</ulink></term>
      <listitem><para>The primary web site for MATE users.  It contains
      release information, downloads, and documentation.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><ulink url="http://library.mate.org/">library.mate.org</ulink></term>
      <listitem><para>The complete source for all MATE documentation.  It contains
      all of the user and developer documentation produced by MATE, automatically
      built and updated for each release.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><ulink url="http://foundation.mate.org/">foundation.mate.org</ulink></term>
      <listitem><para>The web site for the MATE Foundation, the not-for-profit
      foundation that oversees the development of MATE.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><ulink url="http://bugzilla.mate.org/">bugzilla.mate.org</ulink></term>
      <listitem><para>The MATE bug trackers.  Use this site to submit a bug report
      or feature request, or to track the status of a report.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><ulink url="http://live.mate.org/">live.mate.org</ulink></term>
      <listitem><para>The MATE wiki.  Many projects within MATE now use the
      wiki as their primary web space.  In additional, the wiki is often used
      to sketch out future development.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><ulink url="http://developer.mate.org/">developer.mate.org</ulink></term>
      <listitem><para>The old website for developer information.  This once
      contained developer documentation and information about the usability,
      documentation, and translation teams.  The content on this site has
      since been largely superseded by
      <ulink url="http://library.mate.org/">library.mate.org</ulink> and
      <ulink url="http://live.mate.org/">live.mate.org</ulink>.  There may
      still be some information on this site that is not found elsewhere.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><ulink url="http://mail.mate.org/">mail.mate.org</ulink></term>
      <listitem><para>Information on MATE mailing lists.  This site contains
      full archives of all MATE mailing lists.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><ulink url="http://git.mate.org/">git.mate.org</ulink></term>
      <listitem><para>The MATE Git repository, tracking all MATE source code
      back to the inception of the project.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <variablelist>
    <title>Mailing Lists</title>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><ulink
        url="http://mail.mate.org/mailman/listinfo/mate-list">mate-list</ulink></term>
      <listitem><para>The primary mailing list for MATE users.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><ulink
        url="http://mail.mate.org/mailman/listinfo/mate-devel-list">mate-devel-list</ulink></term>
      <listitem><para>Information and questions about development using the
      MATE platform.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><ulink
        url="http://mail.mate.org/mailman/listinfo/mate-love">mate-love</ulink></term>
      <listitem><para>The first place to go to get involved with MATE.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><ulink
        url="http://mail.mate.org/mailman/listinfo/mate-accessibility-list">mate-accessibility-list</ulink></term>
      <listitem><para>Information on accessibility in MATE applications.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><ulink
        url="http://mail.mate.org/mailman/listinfo/mate-doc-list">mate-doc-list</ulink></term>
      <listitem><para>Information on writing documentation for MATE
      applications.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><ulink
        url="http://mail.mate.org/mailman/listinfo/mate-i18n">mate-i18n</ulink></term>
      <listitem><para>Information about internationalization and localization
      of MATE applications.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><ulink
        url="http://mail.mate.org/mailman/listinfo/usability">usability</ulink></term>
      <listitem><para>Information on usability for MATE applications.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <variablelist>
    <title>Conferences</title>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><ulink url="http://guadec.org/">GUADEC</ulink></term>
      <listitem><para>The primary conference for MATE users and developers.
      GUADEC is hosted annually in May or June.  Each year, it is hosted in
      a different European city, making it an excellent excuse to see more
      of Europe.  GUADEC features talks aimed at users, developers, and
      vendors.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>The MATE Summit</term>
      <listitem><para>The hacker get-together.  The Summit is geared
      primarily at existing MATE developers, although there is often
      useful information for new developers.  The Summit is hosted
      annually in Boston.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>MATE.conf.au</term>
      <listitem><para>A casual get-together hosted annually at
      linux.conf.au.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <!-- FIXME: surely there's more -->
  </variablelist>

  <variablelist>
    <title>Other Organizations</title>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><ulink url="http://www.freedesktop.org/">freedesktop.org</ulink></term>
      <listitem><para>The collaborative effort for interoperability and shared
      technology among desktop environments.  Through freedesktop.org, MATE
      works with projects such as KDE and XFCE to make it easier for application
      developers to provide better experiences for their users.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><ulink url="http://www.mozilla.com/">Mozilla</ulink></term>
      <listitem><para>The free web engine, and a whole lot more.  MATE maintains
      close ties to the Mozilla development team to provide an overall better
      user interface.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><ulink url="http://www.openoffice.org/">OpenOffice.org</ulink></term>
      <listitem><para>The free office suite.  MATE works with the OpenOffice.org
      development team to help provide a more unified interface when using the
      free office suite on MATE.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><ulink url="http://www.fsf.org/">Free Software Foundation</ulink></term>
      <listitem><para>Freedom.  Established in 1985, the Free Software
      Foundation has worked to create a complete free operating systems,
      giving its users the freedom to use, modify, and redistribute their
      software.  As part of the GNU project, MATE aims to provide a fully
      free desktop environment.</para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</section>

</chapter>
