<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY appversion "2.28">
<!ENTITY app "<application>mate-bluetooth</application>">
<!ENTITY appname "mate-bluetooth">
<!ENTITY legal SYSTEM "legal.xml">
]>
<article id="index" lang="C">
    <articleinfo>
        <title>mate-bluetooth Manual</title>
        <copyright>
            <year>2009</year>
            <holder>Baptiste Mille-Mathias</holder>
        </copyright>
        
           <legalnotice id="legalnotice">
         <para>
           Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
           document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation
           License (GFDL), Version 1.1 or any later version published
           by the Free Software Foundation with no Invariant Sections,
           no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.  You can find
           a copy of the GFDL at this <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:fdl">link</ulink> or in the file COPYING-DOCS
           distributed with this manual.
          </para>
          <para> This manual is part of a collection of MATE manuals
           distributed under the GFDL.  If you want to distribute this
           manual separately from the collection, you can do so by
           adding a copy of the license to the manual, as described in
           section 6 of the license.
         </para>
 
         <para>
           Many of the names used by companies to distinguish their
           products and services are claimed as trademarks. Where those
           names appear in any MATE documentation, and the members of
           the MATE Documentation Project are made aware of those
           trademarks, then the names are in capital letters or initial
           capital letters.
         </para>
 
         <para>
           DOCUMENT AND MODIFIED VERSIONS OF THE DOCUMENT ARE PROVIDED
           UNDER  THE TERMS OF THE GNU FREE DOCUMENTATION LICENSE
           WITH THE FURTHER UNDERSTANDING THAT:
 
           <orderedlist>
                 <listitem>
                   <para>DOCUMENT IS PROVIDED ON AN "AS IS" BASIS,
                     WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EITHER EXPRESSED OR
                     IMPLIED, INCLUDING, WITHOUT LIMITATION, WARRANTIES
                     THAT THE DOCUMENT OR MODIFIED VERSION OF THE
                     DOCUMENT IS FREE OF DEFECTS MERCHANTABLE, FIT FOR
                     A PARTICULAR PURPOSE OR NON-INFRINGING. THE ENTIRE
                     RISK AS TO THE QUALITY, ACCURACY, AND PERFORMANCE
                     OF THE DOCUMENT OR MODIFIED VERSION OF THE
                     DOCUMENT IS WITH YOU. SHOULD ANY DOCUMENT OR
                     MODIFIED VERSION PROVE DEFECTIVE IN ANY RESPECT,
                     YOU (NOT THE INITIAL WRITER, AUTHOR OR ANY
                     CONTRIBUTOR) ASSUME THE COST OF ANY NECESSARY
                     SERVICING, REPAIR OR CORRECTION. THIS DISCLAIMER
                     OF WARRANTY CONSTITUTES AN ESSENTIAL PART OF THIS
                     LICENSE. NO USE OF ANY DOCUMENT OR MODIFIED
                     VERSION OF THE DOCUMENT IS AUTHORIZED HEREUNDER
                     EXCEPT UNDER THIS DISCLAIMER; AND
                     UNDER NO CIRCUMSTANCES AND UNDER NO LEGAL
                     THEORY, WHETHER IN TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE),
                     CONTRACT, OR OTHERWISE, SHALL THE AUTHOR,
                     INITIAL WRITER, ANY CONTRIBUTOR, OR ANY
                     DISTRIBUTOR OF THE DOCUMENT OR MODIFIED VERSION
                     OF THE DOCUMENT, OR ANY SUPPLIER OF ANY OF SUCH
                     PARTIES, BE LIABLE TO ANY PERSON FOR ANY
                     DIRECT, INDIRECT, SPECIAL, INCIDENTAL, OR
                     CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OF ANY CHARACTER
                     INCLUDING, WITHOUT LIMITATION, DAMAGES FOR LOSS
                     OF GOODWILL, WORK STOPPAGE, COMPUTER FAILURE OR
                     MALFUNCTION, OR ANY AND ALL OTHER DAMAGES OR
                     LOSSES ARISING OUT OF OR RELATING TO USE OF THE
                     DOCUMENT AND MODIFIED VERSIONS OF THE DOCUMENT,
                     EVEN IF SUCH PARTY SHALL HAVE BEEN INFORMED OF
                     THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGES.
                   </para>
                 </listitem>
           </orderedlist>
         </para>
   </legalnotice>
 

        <authorgroup>
            <author role="maintainer">
                <firstname>Baptiste</firstname>
                <surname>Mille-Mathias</surname>
                <affiliation>
                    <orgname>MATE Documentation Project</orgname>
                    <address>
                        <email>baptiste.millemathias@gmail.com</email>
                    </address>
                </affiliation>
            </author>
        </authorgroup>
        
        <!-- According to GNU FDL, revision history is mandatory if you are -->
        <!-- modifying/reusing someone else's document.  If not, you can omit it. -->
        <revhistory>
            <revision>
                <revnumber>1.0</revnumber>
                <date>March 2009</date>
                <revdescription>
                    <para role="author">Baptiste Mille-Mathias
                        <email>baptiste.millemathias@gmail.com</email>
                    </para>
                </revdescription>
            </revision>
            <!-- Uncomment for future revision
		<revision>
		  <revnumber>1.1</revnumber>
		  <date>March 2009</date>
		  <revdescription>
			 <para role="author">Baptiste Mille-Mathias
			     <email>baptiste.millemathias@gmail.com</email></para>
		  </revdescription>
		</revision>
		-->
        </revhistory>
        <releaseinfo>This manual describes version 2.28 of mate-bluetooth.</releaseinfo>
        <legalnotice>
            <title>Feedback</title>
            <para>
                To report a bug or make a suggestion regarding the <application>mate-bluetooth</application> application or this manual, follow the
                directions in the <ulink url="ghelp:user-guide?feedback-bugs" type="help">MATE Feedback
                    Page
                </ulink>
                .
            </para>
        </legalnotice>
        <abstract role="description">
            <para><application>mate-bluetooth</application> is an application to manage Bluetooth devices in the MATE desktop.</para>
        </abstract>
    </articleinfo>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>mate-bluetooth</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>Bluetooth</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm>
        <primary>Communication</primary>
    </indexterm>
    
    <sect1 id="mate-bluetooth-intro">
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>
            <application>mate-bluetooth</application> is an application that let you manage Bluetooth in the MATE destkop.
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <application>mate-bluetooth</application> permits to send files to your Bluetooth devices, or browse their content.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
			Connect to your devices, like headset or audio gateway.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        You can add or delete Bluetooth devices, or manage their permissions.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </para>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1 id="mate-bluetooth-applet">
        <title>Bluetooth Applet</title>
        
        <para>
            The applet is the resident application you can find in the notification applet, that let you quickly access to
            the features, like sending files, or managing your devices.
        </para>
        <figure id="mate-bluetooth-applet-notification">
            <title>Bluetooth Applet icon in notification tray</title>
            <screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="figures/bluetooth-applet.png" format="PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
        </figure>
        
        <sect2 id="mate-bluetooth-applet-start">
            <title>Starting Bluetooth Applet</title>
            
            <para>
                The <application>mate-bluetooth</application> applet is started automatically when you log into your session, and you can find its icon in the
                notification zone. To launch manually the applet, open menu
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>Applications</guimenu><guimenu>Accessories</guimenu><guimenu>Terminal</guimenu>
                </menuchoice>
                and type <command>bluetooth-applet</command>.
            </para>
            <para>
                To prevent launching of the applet in your desktop, open menu
                <menuchoice>
                    <guimenu>System</guimenu><guimenu>Preferences</guimenu><guimenu>Session</guimenu>
                </menuchoice>
                and disable <guilabel>Bluetooth Manager</guilabel>.
            </para>
        </sect2>
        <sect2 id="mate-bluetooh-applet-power">
            <title>Turning off your Bluetooth adapter</title>
            <para>
                Disabling your Bluetooth adapter will stop current and all future communications from and to your Bluetooth
                adapter. Disabling your Bluetooth adapter permits to save power of your laptop's battery, so it'll increase
                the autonomy, this is a good idea to disable your Bluetooth device when you don't use it.
            </para>
            <para>
                Click on the icon of the applet, and choose 
                <menuchoice><guimenu>Turn Off Bluetooth</guimenu></menuchoice>, the notification icon will become grey.
            </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 id="mate-bluetooth-applet-sending">
            <title>Sending files to Bluetooth device</title>
	    <para>
		Choose this menu to send a file to a device; a file chooser will appear to pick up the file to send and
		you'll have to select the device to send the file to.
	    </para>
        </sect2>
        
        <sect2 id="mate-bluetooth-applet-browsing">
            <title>Browsing Bluetooth device</title>
            <para>Choose this menu to browse the device filesystem directly in your file manager.</para>
        </sect2>

	<sect2 id="mate-bluetooth-applet-devices">
	    <title>Last used devices</title>
	    <para>This section displays your paired devices you can connect to.</para>
	    <para>To connect to the device, click on its name, which will become bolded to inform you're connect to it.</para>
	</sect2>
        
        <sect2 id="mate-bluetooth-applet-setup">
            <title>Adding a new device</title>
            
            <para>
                To add a new device (which consist of pairing your adapter with your device), click on the applet icon, and
                choose <guimenu>Setup new device...</guimenu>. An graphical assistant will help you in the process of setting
                up your device.
            </para>
            
            <note>
                <para>
                    Don't forget to set your remote device in discoverable mode before starting the process, else the wizard
                    won't be able to find it.
                </para>
            </note>
            
            <para>
                The wizard will present the discoverable devices it has found all around. You can filter out the list of
                devices by choosing the type of devices you're looking for.
            </para>
            
            <figure id="mate-bluetooth-wizard-img">
                <title>Device search in wizard</title>
                <screenshot>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="figures/bluetooth-wizard.png" format="PNG"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
            </figure>
            
            <para>
                If your device has a harcoded passkey, choose <guibutton>Passkey Options...</guibutton>, in the new
                dialog, choose the passkey to use.
            </para>
            <para>
                Choose <guibutton>Forward</guibutton> for the pairing step; if you defined a fixed passkey in the previous
                step the pairing will occur automatically, else you'll be presented a passkey to enter in your device, type
                it on your device, once done the devices and your adapter will be paired.
            </para>
        </sect2>

        <sect2 id="mate-bluetooth-applet-preferences">
            <title>Preferences</title>
            
            <para>
                Click on the icon of the applet, and choose 
                <menuchoice>
                    <guilabel>Preferences</guilabel>
                </menuchoice>,
                the preferences dialog will appear.
            </para>
            <para>
                For more information about preferences, see section <xref linkend="mate-bluetooth-preferences"/>
            </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1 id="mate-bluetooth-preferences">
        <title>Preferences</title>
        <para>
            The <application>mate-bluetooth</application> preference dialog allows you to manage your various Bluetooth devices or change properties of your
            Bluetooth adapter(s).
        </para>
        
        <figure id="mate-bluetooth-prefs-img">
            <title>Preferences dialog</title>
            <screenshot>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="figures/bluetooth-properties.png" format="PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
        </figure>
            
	<sect2 id="mate-bluetooth-prefs-adapter-discover">
	    <title>Discoverable</title>
	    
	    <para>
		When your adapter is set to <guilabel>Discoverable</guilabel> any Bluetooth device around will be
		able to see it, and therefore will able to ask pairing.
	    </para>
	    <important>
		<para>
		    Bluetooth as other network types implies security risks, so setting your adapter undiscoverable
		    to other devices is a good thing to do to limit the possibility of cracking.
		</para>
	    </important>
	    <para>
		This is only useful to set your device discoverable if you plan to pair it with another device, once
		it is done, you can untick <guilabel>Discoverable</guilabel>.
	    </para>
	    <note>
		<para>
		    When your device is undiscoverable, communication with already paired Bluetooth devices is possible.
		</para>
	    </note>
	</sect2>
	
	<sect2 id="mate-bluetooth-prefs-adapter-name">
	    <title>Adapter friendly name</title>
	    <para>
		The friendly name is an alias for the address used to identified each Bluetooth device much easier
		to remind.
	    </para>
	    <para>
		By default the adapter friendly name is <envar>HOSTNAME</envar>-0 (where <envar>HOSTNAME</envar> is
		the name of your computer), to change it, edit the text entry and set the name you want. the change
		will be immediatly effective.
	    </para>
	</sect2>
	
	<sect2 id="mate-bluetooth-prefs-adapter-devices">
	    <title>Known Devices</title>
	    <para>
		<guilabel>Known devices</guilabel> lists the Bluetooth devices you paired and let you manage them,
		like deleting them, connect to them or adding new one.
		<itemizedlist>
		    <listitem>
			<para>
			    Setup new device, as described in <xref linkend="mate-bluetooth-applet-setup"/>
			</para>
		    </listitem>
		    <listitem>
			<para>
			    Connect / Disconnect to a device.
			</para>
		    </listitem>
		    <listitem>
			<para>
			    Device Deletion. Deletion will suppress pairing between the adapter and the device, and
			    no communication will be allowed. You need to pair them together again if you want transfer
			    files for instance.
			</para>
		    </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	    </para>
	</sect2>
	
	<sect2 id="mate-bluetooth-prefs-show-icon">
	    <title>Show Bluetooth icon</title>
	    <para>
		You can show or hide Bluetooth icon in the panel. See <xref linkend="mate-bluetooth-applet"/> for the
		applet features.
	    </para>
	    
	    <important>
		<para>
		    If you disable the icon in the panel, only limited set of actions will remain available.
		</para>
	    </important>
	</sect2>

	<sect2 id="mate-bluetooth-prefs-receive">
	    <title>Receive Files</title>
	    
	    <para>
		Click on the <guilabel>Receive Files</guilabel> button and the <guilabel>Personal File Sharing Preferences</guilabel> dialog will appear. You can configure Bluetooth file reception and sharing there.
	    </para>
	    <important>
		<para>
		    This feature is not provided by <application>mate-bluetooth</application>.
		    <application>mate-user-share</application> must be installed to use this feature.
		</para>
		<para>
		    Read more in the <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:mate-user-share">Personal File Sharing Manual</ulink>:
		    <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:mate-user-share#mate-user-share-bluetooth-receiving">receiving</ulink> and <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:mate-user-share#mate-user-share-enabling-bluetooth">sharing</ulink>.
		</para>
	    </important>
	</sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1 id="mate-bluetooth-FAQ">
        <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
        <qandaset>
            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para>I don't see how to receive files over Bluetooth on my computer in <application>mate-bluetooth</application>, am I blind?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para>
			File reception is not implemented in <application>mate-bluetooth</application>, but in <application>mate-user-share</application>,
			so you have to install this application to be able to receive files over Bluetooth. Button explained in the <xref linkend="mate-bluetooth-prefs-receive"/> is just a launcher of its configuration dialog.
                    </para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
            <qandaentry>
                <question>
                    <para>I found a bug in <application>mate-bluetooth</application> what I can do?</para>
                </question>
                <answer>
                    <para>
                        You should submit a bug report to <ulink url="http://bugzilla.mate.org/enter_bug.cgi?product=mate-bluetooth"/>.
                    </para>
                </answer>
            </qandaentry>
            <!--
	  <qandaentry>
	      <question>
		  <para></para>
	      </question>
	      <answer>
		  <para></para>
	      </answer>
	  </qandaentry>-->
        </qandaset>
    </sect1>
    
    
</article>
