<sect1 id="config-behavior">
  <title>Toolbars and Menus</title>
  <para>
    <application>Mate</application> allows for the user to configure
    many settings of their desktop.  Anything from the background
    image to where buttons are located can be set.  The
    <guilabel>Behavior</guilabel> window is responsible for a lot of
    the finer settings.
  </para>
  <para>
    If you open up the <guilabel>Behavior</guilabel> window, you'll
    find a few options at your disposal to make your
    <application>Mate</application> experience better.
  </para>
  <sect2 id="config-behavior-toolbar">
    <title>Toolbar Options</title>
    <para>
      The top half of the window shows you toolbar options.
    </para>
    <para>
      In the <guilabel>Toolbars have</guilabel> section, you'll see
      three options available: Icons and Text, Only Icons, Only Text.
    </para>
    <para>
      The Icons and Text makes the toolbars display both icons and
      text.  While this takes up the most space, it is the most
      informative.
    </para>
    <para>
      The Only Icons options makes the toolbars show only icons.  This
      isn't the most descriptive, but helps save space.
    </para>
    <para>
      The Only Text options is the most simple options.  However, it
      is easily the most descriptive option.
    </para>
    <para>
      Below that option is a button called <guibutton>Toolbars can be
      detached and moved around</guibutton>.  This allows you to take
      a toolbar off the window and place it anywhere in the screen you
      wish.  You can demo this in the <guilabel>Sample
      Toolbar</guilabel> below.  On the left side is a textured bar.
      Click that and drag around the screen.  That toolbar will detach
      and be dropped where you let go of the cursor.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="config-behavior-menus">
    <title>Menu Options</title>
    <para>
      Menus can also be configured.  You can have menu items have
      icons.  This is nice to help identify what things do.
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>