<sect1 id="cfg-default-applications">
  <title>Default Applications</title>
  <sect2 id="cfg-default-applications-introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      The <application>Default Applications</application> capplet
      sets up some of the default programs to use for different
      events.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="cfg-default-applications-txt-editor">
    <title>Text Editor Defaults</title>
    <para>
      Your default text editor is used when a plain text file needs to
      be opened for either viewing or editing.  
      </para>
    <para>
      By default,
      <application>gedit</application> is used as the text editor.
      However, as text editors are installed, more options are added
      to the <guilabel>Select an Editor</guilabel> pull-down
      list. Once you've selected your text editor, click
      <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to save your settings.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can also set a custom editor when your desired editor isn't
      in the pulldown menu.  You select the <guibutton>Custom
      Editor</guibutton> radio button and enter the text editor name.
      If you wish, you can have the editor open in a terminal window
      by selecting the <guibutton>Start in Terminal</guibutton>
      button.  Clicking <guibutton>Accepts Line Number</guibutton>
      lets MATE pass a line number to the editor so that you can
      "warp" to a part of a file.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="cfg-default-applications-www">
    <title>Web Browser Defaults</title>
    <para>
      Your default web browser is refered to when you click on a link
      that directs to a web site.
    </para>
    <para>
      By default, <application>Netscape 6/Mozilla</application> is
      used to view HTML files.  However, as more browsers are
      installed, more choices will become available to use.  Choose
      your browser by selecting the right item in the <guilabel>Select
      a Web Browser</guilabel> section.  Once you
      have made your change, click <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to apply
      your changes.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can also specify a custom web browser to use by selecting
      the <guibutton>Custom Web Browser</guibutton> radio button.
      Enter the command to execute your browser in the
      <guilabel>Command</guilabel> entry area.  By clicking
      <guibutton>Start in Terminal</guibutton>, the application will
      start in a termainal.  To do remote commands in
      <application>Netscape</application> select the
      <guibutton>Understands Netscape Remote Control</guibutton>
      button.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="cfg-default-applications-hlp-view">
    <title>Help Viewer Defaults</title>
    <para>
      The help browser is called when a help file is needed to be
      displayed.  Help files are available normally through either the
      <guibutton>Help</guibutton> button located in some windows or
      the <guilabel>Help</guilabel> menu.
    </para>
    <para>
      By default, two help browsers are located in the
      <guilabel>Select a Viewer</guilabel> section:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Mate Help Browser ("GHB")
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Caja
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      You can change the default viewer by selecting an item in the
      drop-down menu and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.
    </para>
    <para>
      There is a possibility though that you will want to use a help
      browser not included in the list.  Click the <guibutton>Custom
      Help Viewer</guibutton> radio button and enter the command to
      run in the <guilabel>Command</guilabel> field.  By clicking
      <guibutton>Start in Terminal</guibutton>, the application will
      start in a termainal.  The <guibutton>Accepts URLs</guibutton>
      should normally be turned on, saying that it can dual as a web
      browser.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="cfg-default-apps-terminal">
    <title>Terminal Defaults</title>
    <para>
      Your terminal window will sometimes be brought up to execute
      commands.  For example, if you select to have an application be
      brought up in the console, the terminal defaults will be
      called.  Numerous defaults for terminals exist; the default
      being <application>Mate Terminal</application>.  Select a
      terminal from the list and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Sometimes, you may want to use a terminal which isn't listed in
      the prelisted items.  Click <guibutton>Custom
      Terminal</guibutton> and enter the command to run your terminal
      in the <guilabel>Command</guilabel> section.  The <guilabel>Exec
      Flag</guilabel> option says how to embed a program in the
      terminal.  Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to apply your preferences.
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>