<sect1 id="config-keyboard">
  <title>Keyboard</title>
  <para>
    Everyone uses the keyboard for their daily tasks.  Most people
    think that there isn't much to configuring a keyboard.  Quite the
    contrary.  There are numerous keyboard options which can be set to
    make your experience more comfortable.
  </para>
  <sect2 id="config-keyboard-keyboard">
    <title>Keyboard Behavior Configuration</title>
    <para>
      The keyboard's behavior is controlled thorugh the
      <guilabel>Keyboard</guilabel> tab.  The following options are
      available:
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Keyboard repeats when key is held down</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      All keyboards have the ability to rapidly repeat a
	      keystroke on the screen if a key is held down.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Delay before repeat:</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      There is normally a delay between when the keyboard key
	      is pressed and when the repeat is displayed on the
	      screen.  You can choose:
	      <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Short
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Medium
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Long
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Very Long
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </itemizedlist>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Repeat speed</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      While a keystroke is being repeated, you can control how
	      fast the repeat is.  The available speeds are:
	      <itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Slow
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Medium
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Fast
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>
		    Very Fast
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	      </itemizedlist>
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Cursor blinks in text fields</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      The keyboard cursor sometimes blinks to help show you
	      where it is located.  The blinking can be turned off
	      entirely by deselecting this option.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Blink speed</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      You can configure the speed at which the cursor blinks.
	      Sliding this right will cause the cursor to blink
	      faster, while sliding it left will cause the cursor to
	      blink at a slower speed.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="config-kbd-sound">
    <title>Keyboard Sound Options</title>
    <para>
      The keyboard sometimes emits sounds to get the user's
      attention.  The sounds can be configured in the
      <guilabel>Sound</guilabel> tab.
      <variablelist>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Keypress makes sound</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      You can set your keyboard up so when you hit a key, it
	      will make a sound.  Click this button to enable it.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Volume</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      You can also control the volume that the click happens
	      at.  Move the slider to the right for maximum volume,
	      and left for minimum volume.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Keyboard bell off</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      If you wish to disable the keyboard bell, select this
	      radio box.  This is good for situations where you need
	      quiet, like a class or a library.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Keyboard bell enabled</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      Select this radio box to enable the keyboard bell.  This
	      will make the computer speaker beep when it needs to get
	      your attention.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
	  <term>Custom keyboard bell</term>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>
	      You can have the system play a customized sound instead
	      of the default system beep.  Select this radio button
	      and press the <guibutton>Browse</guibutton> button to
	      select the file you want.  Press the
	      <guibutton>Done</guibutton> button to apply your changes.
	    </para>
	  </listitem>
	</varlistentry>	  
      </variablelist>
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>