<sect1 id="config-cd">
  <title>Audio CDs</title>
  <para>
    Mate can play your CDs on your computer.  You can setup you
    CD preferences in the <guibutton>CD Properties</guibutton> capplet
    in the <guilabel>Advanced</guilabel> section of the
    <application>Mate Control Center</application>.  
  </para>
  <para>
    Once open, you'll see the window is broken into two sections: Data
    CDs and Audio CDs.
  </para>
  <sect2 id="config-cd-data">
    <title>Data CDs</title>
    <para>
      Data CDs are CDs which hold information that the system can
      execute.  These often times include CDs that have programs or a
      CD which you burned family pictures to. 
    </para>
    <para>
      The first option is <guibutton>Automatically mount CD when
      inserted</guibutton>.  By enabling this option, you can have
      your CD auto-detected when you insert it.
    </para>
    <tip>
      <title>What is mounting</title>
      <para>
	Linux and Unix systems use a term called mounting to identify
	recognizing a device.  If you "mount" your CD-ROM, that means
	that your system can recognize the CD-ROM and you can interact
	with it.  If it us unmounted, then the system does not know of
	its existance and can do almost nothing with it.
      </para>
    </tip>
    <para>
      The second option, <guibutton>Automatically start auto-run
      program on newly mounted CD</guibutton> allows the system to run
      the program on the CD automatically when the disk is first mounted.
    </para>
    <para>
      The last option, <guibutton>Open file manager window for newly
      mounted CD</guibutton> tells the system to open your file
      manager (<application>Caja</application> by default) when the
      CD is mounted.  This is useful if you have a CD of images from
      your family reunion you wish to browse.  It will open up in
      <application>Caja</application> which will let you view the
      thumbnails.
    </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="config-cd-audio">
    <title>Audio CDs</title>
    <para>
      The <guilabel>Audio CDs</guilabel> section has only one option.
      This allows the system to load up a CD player when you insert
      the CD.  You simply click the checkbox and enter the command you
      wish to run in the input dialog.
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
	Audio CDs don't need to be mounted to play the CD.
      </para>
    </note>
  </sect2>
</sect1>